Emington, Ill. Emington Congregational Church records, 1875-2021.
Congregational Library & Archives
Emington, Ill. Emington Congregational Church records, 1875-2021.
RG5433
Congregational Library & Archives
5.98 Cubic Feet
(7 boxes)
The Emington Congregational Church in Emington, Illinois, was established on March 23, 1875. The church building was moved from farmland to the center of Emington in 1881. A new church was built on the same location between 1905 and 1906 to accommodate the growing congregation. The church shared ministry with the Dwight Congregational Church briefly in 1931 and more permanently with the Odell Congregational Church starting in 1955. The church joined the United Church of Christ in 1964 and closed in 2021. This archival collection contains records which document the operation of the church as well as records which document the activities of the members of the church. The collection includes meeting minutes, auxiliary group records, financial records, and vital membership records.
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Emington Congregational Church in March 2022; 2022-06.
Historical Note
The Emington Congregational Church was established on March 23, 1875, though some of the the initial members of the church had been worshipping together since at least 1868. The original church building had been an unused church at Cedar Point. The building was disassembled and then reassembled at a farm outside Emington. In 1881 the building was moved once again into the center of Emington where the Emington Congregational Church would remain until its eventual closure.
By 1905, the church community had outgrown their edifice and decided to build a new building. Construction began in 1905 and was completed in 1906. A fire damaged part of the roof of the church in 1927. A parsonage was built on the church's land in 1929. The Emington Congregational Church temporarily shared a minister with the Dwight Congregational Church starting in 1931. A more permanent shared ministry with the Odell Congregational Church was begun in 1955 with Rev. Esra Vornholt serving as pastor of both churches. The church joined the United Church of Christ on January 28, 1964. The church closed in 2021.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of the Emington Congregational Church in Emington, Illinois and includes records which document the operation of the church as well as records which document the activities of the members of the church. The records include meeting minutes, financial records, building records, annual reports, and various versions of the church's by-laws and constitutions. The collection has extensive records relating to the church's Sunday School as well as the church's Ladies Aid Society. In addition to these two groups, the collection contains records for various church auxiliary groups. The records also include membership records and lists, baptismal records, photographs of the church building, people, and events, guest books, and member memorials.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the five series listed below. Within each series, materials have been arranged into chronological order by start date.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1875-2021
Series 2: Membership records, 1888-2019
Series 3: Sunday school records, 1893-1996
Series 4: Ladies aid society records, 1902-2007
Series 4: Programs and auxiliary group records, 1903-2015
Bibliography
The First 100 Years: Emington Congregational Church (United Church of Christ) of Emington, Illinois. 1975.
- Administrative records, 1875 2021; 1875-2021; 11 Volumes; 29 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administration and operation of the Emington Congregational Church. The records include church meeting minutes, annual reports, board of trustees minutes, financial records, pastoral reports and communications, correspondence, constitutions and by-laws, and yearbook reports.
  - Legal recordsI, 1875 1992; 1875-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Church records, 1887 1918; 1887-1900, 1918 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Church records, 1901 1957; 1901-1957 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Financial records, 1905 1907; 1905-1907 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Financial statements, 1909 1924; 1909, 1922-1924 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Financial records, 1910 1964; 1910-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Financial records, 1929 1958; 1929-1958 (Box 2, Volume 9)
  - Search committee report, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Yearbook reports, 1938 1972; 1938-1972 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Pastor's reports, 1940 1941; 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous meeting minutes, 1940 1948; 1940-1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1953 2021; 1953-2021 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Esra R. Vornholt communications and reports, 1955 1959; 1955-1959 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Conference communications, 1957 1958; 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Drawings, 1957 1982; 1957, 1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Financial records, 1960 1962; 1960-1962 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Church records, 1960 1983; 1960-1983 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Board of trustees records, 1962 1970; 1962-1970 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Annual reports, 1962 1971; 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Financial records, 1963 1966; 1963-1966 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Miscellaneous reports, 1964, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Organ certificate, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Financial records, 1967 1970; 1967-1970 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Constitution, by-laws, and job descriptions, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Board of trustees records, 1969 1974; 1969-1974 (Box 1, Volume 4)
    Separated Materials
    Loose materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folder labeled "Board of trustees records, 1973-1975" to assist in the preservation of those materials.
  - Deacons, 1972 1973; 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Board of deacons and deaconesses records, 1972 1974; 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Annual reports, 1972 1981; 1972-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of trustees records, 1973 1975; 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    These loose materials were removed from the "Board of trustees records, 1969-1974" for preservation purposes.
  - Board of trustees records, 1975 1991; 1975-1991 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Annual reports, 1982 1991; 1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Church meeting minutes, 1983 1989; 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Church meeting minutes, 1990 1996; 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual reports, 1992 2001; 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Church meeting minutes, 1997 2008; 1997-2008 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Annual reports, 2002 2011; 2002-2011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Constitution, by-laws, and statement of faith, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Annual reports, 2012 2021; 2012-2021 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Yoked parish agreement, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Membership records, 1888 2019; 1888-2019; 3 Volumes; 14 Folders
  This series contains vital membership records and records related to the general activities of members of the Emington Congregational Church. The records include birth and baptismal records, family records, membership records and lists, newspaper clippings, remembrances and memorials, and photographic materials.
  - Family records, 1888 1986; 1888-1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Vital member records, 1890 1961; 1890-1961 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Birth records, 1915 1923; 1915-1923 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - Miscellaneous vital records, 1925 1984; 1925-1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Baptismal and membership certificates, 1939 1943; 1939-1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1940 1995; 1940-1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Remembrances, 1944 1995; 1944-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Service certificates, 1946 1949; 1946, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Membership list, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Vital member records, 1962 2007; 1962-2007 (Box 1, Volume 12)
  - Dedication for memorials, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Centenial photographs, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Guest book, 2018 2019; circa 2018-2019 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Church bulletins, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - People and event photographic materials, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Church building photographic materials, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Glass plates, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Sunday school records, 1893 1996; 1893-1996; 66 Volumes; 5 Folders
  This series contains records related to the Sunday School at the Emington Congregational Church. The records include teacher's records, attendance records, and meeting minutes.
  - Sunday school teacher info cards, 1893 1958; 1893-1958 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sunday school records, 1893 1896; 1893-1896 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - Sunday school records, 1900 1901; 1900-1901 (Box 5, Volume 2)
  - Sunday school records, 1902 1904; 1902-1904 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Sunday school records, 1905 1910; 1905-1910 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Sunday school class books, 1905 1970; circa 1905-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sunday school records, 1906 (Box 5, Volume 3)
  - Sunday school class books, 1906 1958; 1906-1958 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sunday school records, 1911 1919; 1911-1919 (Box 4, Volume 1)
  - Sunday school records, 1918 (Box 5, Volume 4)
  - Sunday school records, 1921 (Box 5, Volume 5)
  - Sunday school records, 1921 1922; 1921-1922 (Box 5, Volume 6)
  - Sunday school records, 1921 1923; 1921-1923 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1923 1924; 1923-1924 (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1924 (Box 4, Volume 3)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1925 (Box 4, Volume 4)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1926 (Box 4, Volume 5)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1927 (Box 4, Volume 6)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1928 (Box 4, Volume 7)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1929 (Box 4, Volume 8)
  - Miscellaneous Sunday school records, 1929 1973; 1929-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1930 (Box 4, Volume 9)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1931 (Box 4, Volume 10)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1932 (Box 4, Volume 11)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1933 (Box 4, Volume 12)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1934 (Box 4, Volume 13)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1935 (Box 4, Volume 14)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 15)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1937 (Box 4, Volume 16)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1938 (Box 4, Volume 17)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1939 (Box 4, Volume 18)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1940 (Box 4, Volume 19)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1941 (Box 4, Volume 20)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1942 (Box 4, Volume 21)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1943 (Box 4, Volume 22)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1944 (Box 4, Volume 23)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1945 (Box 4, Volume 24)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1946 (Box 4, Volume 25)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1947 (Box 4, Volume 26)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1948 (Box 4, Volume 27)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1949 (Box 4, Volume 28)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1950 (Box 4, Volume 29)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1951 (Box 4, Volume 30)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1952 (Box 4, Volume 31)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1953 (Box 4, Volume 32)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1954 (Box 4, Volume 33)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1955 (Box 5, Volume 7)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1956 (Box 5, Volume 8)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1957 (Box 5, Volume 9)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1958 (Box 5, Volume 10)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1959 (Box 5, Volume 11)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1960 (Box 5, Volume 12)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1961 (Box 5, Volume 13)
  - Sunday school class books, 1961 1996; 1961-1970, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1962 (Box 5, Volume 14)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1963 (Box 5, Volume 15)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1964 (Box 5, Volume 16)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1965 (Box 5, Volume 17)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1966 (Box 5, Volume 18)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1967 (Box 5, Volume 19)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1968 (Box 5, Volume 20)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1969 (Box 5, Volume 21)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1970 (Box 5, Volume 22)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1971 1972; 1971-1972 (Box 5, Volume 23)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1972 1973; 1972-1973 (Box 5, Volume 24)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1973 1974; 1973-1974 (Box 5, Volume 25)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1975 (Box 5, Volume 26)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1976 1977; 1976-1977 (Box 5, Volume 27)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1977 1978; 1977-1978 (Box 5, Volume 28)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1979 1980; 1979-1980 (Box 5, Volume 29)
  - Sunday school secretary book, 1980 1981; 1980-1981 (Box 5, Volume 30)
- Ladies aid society records, 1902 2007; 1902-2007; 18 Volumes; 8 Folders
  This series contains records related to the Ladies aid society of the Emington Congregational Church. The records include the meeting minutes for the auxiliary group as well as financial records, correspondence, and an early copy of the group's by-laws.
  - Ladies aid society records, 1902 1910; 1902-1910 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    Loose materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folder labeled "Ladies aid society by-laws, 1914" to assist in the preservation of those materials.
  - Ladies aid society records, 1911 1919; 1911-1919 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Ladies aid society by-laws, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    These loose materials were removed from the "Ladies aid society records, 1902-1910" for preservation purposes.
  - Ladies aid society records, 1919 1923; 1919-1923 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1924 1932; 1924-1932 (Box 3, Volume 3)
    Loose materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folder labeled "Ladies aid society correspondence, 1933-1940" to assist in the preservation of those materials.
  - Ladies aid society records, 1933 1939; 1933-1939 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Ladies aid society correspondence, 1933 1940; 1933-1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    These loose materials were removed from the "Ladies aid society records, 1924-1932" for preservation purposes.
  - Ladies aid society records, 1939 1943; 1939-1943 (Box 2, Volume 6)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1943 1946; 1943-1946 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1947 1950; 1947-1950 (Box 3, Volume 6)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1950 1954; 1950-1954 (Box 3, Volume 7)
    Loose materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folder labeled "Ladies aid society reports, 1951-1953" to assist in the preservation of those materials.
  - Ladies aid society reports, 1951 1953; 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    These loose materials were removed from the "Ladies aid society records, 1950-1954" for preservation purposes.
  - Ladies aid society records, 1954 1958; 1954-1958 (Box 3, Volume 8)
    Loose materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folder labeled "Ladies aid society treasurer reports, 1955, 1957" to assist in the preservation of those materials.
  - Ladies aid society treasurer reports, 1955 1957; 1955, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    These loose materials were removed from the "Ladies aid society records, 1954-1958" for preservation purposes.
  - Ladies aid society records, 1958 1964; 1958-1964 (Box 3, Volume 9)
  - Ladies aid society collections book, 1959 (Box 3, Volume 14)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1960 1966; 1960-1966 (Box 3, Volume 15)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1965 1968; 1965-1968 (Box 3, Volume 10)
  - Ladies aid society financial records, 1967 1975; 1967-1975 (Box 3, Volume 16)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1969 1972; 1969-1972 (Box 3, Volume 11)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1973 1975; 1973-1975 (Box 3, Volume 12)
  - Ladies aid society financial records, 1976 2008; 1976-2008 (Box 3, Volume 13)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1980 1988; 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ladies aid society records, 1989 2007; 1989-2007 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ladies aid society financial records, 1990 1998; 1990-1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ladies aid society financial records, 1995 2003; 1995-2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Programs and auxiliary group records, 1903 2015; 1903-2015; 7 Volumes; 16 Folders
  This series contains records related to various auxiliary groups at the Emington Congregational Church as well as programs and events held by the church. The records include Christian Endeavor records, Little Six Pilgrim League records, Study guild minutes, Pilgrim fellowship records, Men's fellowship records, Memorial and Historical committee records, a book related to the mother-daughter banquet held at the church, records and programs related to church anniversaries, Happy hour study group records, and Friendship circle records.
  - Christian Endeavor booklet, 1903 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Christian Endeavor Society records, 1903 1913; 1903-1907, 1913 (Box 2, Volume 7)
  - Christian Endeavor Society records, 1917 1925; 1917-1925 (Box 2, Volume 8)
  - Congregational Education Society certificate, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Little Six Pilgrim League records, 1937 1940; 1937-1940 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Study guild minutes, 1954 1973; 1954-1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Anniversaries, 1955 2015; 1955-2015 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Pilgrim fellowship records, 1961 1963; 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pilgrim fellowship records, 1962 1970; 1962-1970 (Box 3, Volume 17)
  - Men's Fellowship book, 1962 1967; 1962-1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Vacation Bible school records, 1962 1975; 1962-1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Memorial fund book, 1963 1974; 1963-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 90th anniversary guest book, 1965 (Box 2, Volume 10)
  - Mother-daughter banquet book, 1969 1973; 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Memorial committee records, 1971 1975; 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    A 1974 letter was removed from the very front of the "Memorial committee records, 1974-1983" volume and placed into this folder for preservation purposes.
  - Memorial committee records, 1974 1983; 1974-1983 (Box 3, Volume 18)
    A 1974 letter was removed from the very beginning of this volume and placed into the folder labeled "Memorial committee records, 1971-1975" to assist in the preservation of that item.
  - Historical committee records, 1975 1976; 1975-1976 (Box 3, Volume 19)
  - Happy hour study group records, 1980 1985; 1980-1985 (Box 3, Volume 20)
    Loose materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folder labeled "Happy hour study group records, undated" to assist in the preservation of those materials.
  - Friendship circle, 2007 2013; 2007-2013 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Happy hour study group records, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    These loose materials were removed from the "Happy hour study group records, 1980-1985" for preservation purposes.
  - List of filmstrips, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Program evaluation questionnaire, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Pilgrim fellowship constitution, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)